<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hainousness of injustice done under the pretence of equity in a sermon preach'd in the cathedral church of Lincoln, before the honourable Baron Turton, at the assizes holden for that county on Monday the eighth of August, 1698. By Laurence Echard, A.M. prebendary of Lincoln, and chaplain to the right reverend James lord bishop of that diocese.</title>
            <author>Echard, Laurence, 1670?-1730.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897238</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897238</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82726)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2483:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hainousness of injustice done under the pretence of equity in a sermon preach'd in the cathedral church of Lincoln, before the honourable Baron Turton, at the assizes holden for that county on Monday the eighth of August, 1698. By Laurence Echard, A.M. prebendary of Lincoln, and chaplain to the right reverend James lord bishop of that diocese.</title>
                  <author>Echard, Laurence, 1670?-1730.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for M. Wotton at the Three Daggers in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XI, 1 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135143:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Hainouſneſs of Injuſtice Done under the Pretence of EQUITY: IN A SERMON Preach'd in the Cathedral Church of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> Before the Honourable BARON <hi>TURTON,</hi> At the <hi>ASSIZES</hi> holden for that County on <hi>Monday</hi> the Eighth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1698.</p>
            <p>By <hi>LAURENCE ECHARD,</hi> A. M. Prebendary of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Reverend <hi>James</hi> Lord Biſhop of that Dioceſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>M. Wotton</hi> at the <hi>Three Daggers</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:135143:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135143:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>VVHEN I preach'd this Sermon, I had no Thoughts of publiſhing it; nor was it the Advice or Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Friends that occaſion'd it now. I was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that it was compos'd with too much Haſte and Careleſneſs, to deſerve a Publick View, when ſo many correct Sermons were already extant. But immediately after, finding my Reputation in ſome Hazard by Means of the Miſunderſtandings of ſome, and the Miſrepreſentations of others, I thought I cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d do no greater Juſtice to my ſelf than to publiſh it, and ſo rectifie Peoples Miſtakes; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as aroſe from ſecond and third Hand Stories. It ſeems ſeveral <hi>Trades-men</hi> as well as <hi>Lawyers</hi> were not well pleas'd with ſome Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages; and therefore cenſur'd me as a Perſon too Reflecting and Unmannerly to my Superiors: And that theſe Cenſures might ſeem juſt, my Words
<pb facs="tcp:135143:3"/> and Senſe were much miſrepreſented, and ſeveral Paſſages related and diſcours'd of that were never in my Sermon. In ſum, this is the Reaſon for my pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing this Sermon, which I have done juſt as it was preach'd, without any material Alteration. And ſince it made ſuch a ſenſible Impreſſion upon ſome, as to take notice of it to my Diſadvantage, I hope the Publication of it may occaſion ſome others to take notice of it to their own Advantage.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135143:3"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PROV. xi. 1.</bibl> A falſe Balance is an Abomination to the Lord: but a juſt Weight is his Delight.</q>
            </head>
            <p>AS the Proverbs and Sayings of the wiſe Author of this Book are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally remarkable for being diſtinct and independent of each other; ſo they are no leſs remarkable for being often figurative, and of a very ſtrong and extenſive Meaning. So the Words of this Text; tho' they can li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally ſignifie nothing but the Odiouſneſs of a falſe Weight or Balance in particular, yet they have truly and naturally a more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd and diffuſive Senſe, and do imply the Odiouſneſs not only of falſe Weights and Balances, but likewiſe of all Things of the like Nature and Conſequence; of all unfair and unfaithful Actions, of all unequal and injurious Proceedings, and of all falſe and irregular Diſtributions of Juſtice. In ſum, this Text, according to the general Meaning of its Words, does enjoin that great Vertue and Duty of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> a Quality which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135143:4"/> from, and eſſential to the Great Judge of Heaven and Earth, and is as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſibly neceſſary for the Subſiſtence and Well-being of Mankind in this World, as for their eternal Felicity in the next.</p>
            <p>But tho' theſe Words do ſtrictly prohibit all falſe and unequal Diſtributions of Juſtice both in Private as well as Publick Perſons, yet they are not ſo properly to be extended to all Kinds of Injuſtice whatſoever. They relate indeed to the moſt and worſt Kinds of Injuſtice, but not ſo poſitively and directly to all. For, as it has been obſerv'd by many, there are Two ſeveral Kinds of Injuſtice; the One open and bare-fac'd, without any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings for its native Crookedneſs and Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; and the Other ſecret and diſguis'd, ſo cunningly cloath'd and adorn'd, that it appears like Juſtice its ſelf: The One depends chiefly upon Force and Power, and the Other upon Treachery and Infidelity: The Former carries no Pretence with it beſides that of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying and profiting the Actor, and the Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter has always the plauſible Appearance of doing Juſtice to the ſame Perſon it really in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jures. Now the Words of my Text are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to manifeſt the Odiouſneſs and Hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of this latter Kind; and do elegantly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135143:4"/> repreſent it under the Notion of a <hi>falſe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance.</hi> For a falſe Balance is always made uſe of under the plauſible Pretence of doing of Juſtice, tho' it has a contrary Effect; and whenſoever it wants that Pretence, the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairneſs is detected, it loſes its original Deſign, and conſequently ceaſes to be injurious.</p>
            <p>To make a fuller and clearer Diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two Kinds of Injuſtice, we may obſerve, That to the former Kind belong all Rapines and open Violence, all Robberies and Murders, and all unjuſt Plunderings and Devaſtations; to which we may add all thoſe particular Acts of Injuſtice which our Laws call <hi>Thefts.</hi> Theſe laſt indeed are generally tranſacted with the utmoſt Privacy and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy, yet the Injuſtice is undiſguis'd and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd, and they are not done with the Pretence of doing of Juſtice to thoſe Perſons they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure; nor have they the ſame treacherous and pernicious Circumſtances as belong to the latter Kind of Injuſtice, of which I am prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to treat.</p>
            <p>This latter Kind, ſetting aſide Murders and Violence offer'd to Mens Bodies, is no leſs hurtful and injurious than the Other, and at the ſame time more deceitful and ungenerous; conſiſting of ſuch particular Acts of Injuſtice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135143:5"/> as have always a fair, and very often a lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Appearance. So that this is not bare and ſimple Injuſtice alone, but Injuſtice mix'd with, or wrapp'd up in ſome Act of Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Infidelity, and Villany. Of this Kind are all falſe Weights and Meaſures, all Cheats and Over-reachings in Bargains, all Breaches of Truſt and Infidelity, with an infinite Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of others of the like Nature; only we muſt not omit all unequal and falſe Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Juſtice, eſpecially by ſuch to whom the Adminiſtration belongs, and where a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and publick Good is concern'd.</p>
            <p>Having thus diſtinguiſh'd between theſe two Kinds of Injuſtice, and ſhown that there is a manifeſt Difference, it will not be impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to my preſent Deſign to compare them together, and to examine which is the moſt hainous of the two, and the moſt deteſtable in the Eyes of God. And I queſtion not but I may eaſily make it appear, that the Latter, which is the Subject of my Diſcourſe, is of a far more criminal Nature than the Former, and is therefore emphatically ſaid to be <hi>an Abomination to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Kind is more abominable than the other, Firſt in its <hi>Nature,</hi> and Secondly in its <hi>Conſequences.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:135143:5"/>
            <p>Firſt, It is more abominable in its <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> And it will appear from the former Diſtinction, That this is a Complication of Crimes and Miſchiefs, whilſt the other is only Simple Injuſtice. This is a Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of many Impieties together, and thoſe of the meaneſt and baſeſt Kind; the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is only one ſingle Act of Wickedneſs, without any Concomitants of Treachery and Infidelity. Open Violence and Robberies have ſometimes the Appearance of Courage and Bravery, and have ſome Reſemblance of the Acts of Heroes; but the Other are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways vile and ungenerous, and will ever be accounted the Acts of Villains. But to ſet the Compariſon in a truer Light, and to give neither of them any ſpecious Names, the Former reſembles the Actions of a ſavage Beaſt, that cannot exceed the Bounds of its own Strength; but the Latter the Subtleties of the Devil, of whoſe Artifices we know no Limits.</p>
            <p>Smaller Thefts are indeed of a meaner and more ungenerous Nature than open Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet ſtill they are generally as unmix'd, and are bare Acts of Injuſtice without any Pretence of Fairneſs and Fidelity. He who privately ſteals my Goods, or picks my Pocket,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135143:6"/> does a great Act of Injuſtice, but he does me no other Injury than the Value of the Goods or Money amounts to, and adds no other Sin to this: But he who cheats me in his Shop by falſe Weights, falſe Stories, and falſe Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, does the ſame Injuſtice and Injury to me as the other; but then, as an Addition to his Crime, he picks my Pocket more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely and ſecurely, impoſes upon my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and common Faculties, and joins Lying and other Sins to his Injuſtice. So that it is apparent, That this Kind of Injuſtice is far more criminal in its very <hi>Nature</hi> than the other; not only becauſe it is viler and more baſe, but alſo becauſe it has the Addition of many other Crimes and aggravating Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances from which the other is free. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, This Kind is more abominable than the other in its <hi>Conſequences;</hi> one of which is, That we have far leſs Security againſt theſe Kind of unjuſt Actors, than we have againſt the other; ſo that the Miſchiefs of it are more certain and inevitable, which is always a Circumſtance that makes a Crime more odious in the Preſence of God. Force can repel Force, but it cannot repel Treachery. We have Arms to ſtop the Fury of Robbers, Locks to prevent the Pilferings of Thieves,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135143:6"/> and ſtrict Laws to ſecure us againſt the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of both; which, God be thanked, has been ſo effectual, that our Nation in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral has not ſuffer'd any great and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Miſchiefs from either: But no Arms, no Locks, nor no Laws can ſecure us from the various Miſchiefs and Subtleties of a thorow-pac'd Villain. Nay, Laws will give us no Relief in many common and notorious Acts of Injuſtice. If a poor Wretch ſteals a ſmall Quantity of Goods, perhaps to cover his Nakedneſs, or to ſatisfie his Hunger, he ſhall certainly be puniſh'd for it: But ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon ſhall be permitted to ſteal what he pleaſes in his own Shop, in his Bargains, and after the like manner, without any Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment or Cenſure from the Laws.</p>
            <p>Now what is the Reaſon of the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, but only this? One is accounted <hi>Theft</hi> according to Law, and the Other not. But this makes not the Crime the leſs, but the greater before God; <hi>who judgeth not as Man judgeth,</hi> but reſerves ſuch Caſes as theſe for his peculiar Judgment and Puniſhment. I ſpeak not this to extenuate the Actions of Thieves, or to expoſe any Deficiencies in our Laws, which I grant cannot be made to reach all unjuſt Actions; but to ſhow, That this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135143:7"/> Kind of Injuſtice is more hainous before God, not only in its <hi>Nature,</hi> but likewiſe in its <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences;</hi> ſince the Miſchiefs and Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies of the one are more unavoidable than thoſe of the other. Upon which Account it is, that God, as I juſt now hinted, does in a great meaſure reſerve Caſes of this Nature for his own peculiar Tribunal in the laſt and dreadful Day; and therefore he has more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and with greater Threatnings mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his Diſpleaſure againſt this Kind of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice than the Other; and particularly in the Words of my Text, where we are told, That it is <hi>an Abomination to</hi> Him; a Word that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies an extraordinary Degree of Hatred and Deteſtation.</p>
            <p>But now to approach a little nearer to this preſent Publick Occaſion.—If all Acts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice be odious in God's Sight, even in the meaneſt and moſt private Perſon, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as are wrought by ſecret Springs, and under the Pretence of doing of Juſtice; then certainly thoſe muſt be exceedingly hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous before God that are done by Publick Perſons, and in a Publick Capacity, whoſe Employment it is to eſtabliſh all Things with the utmoſt Impartiality, and to ſee that no Injuſtice be done in a Nation. I hope I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135143:7"/> not, if I ſay, that I now mean the <hi>Judges</hi> of the Kingdom; Perſons from whom we receive ineſtimable Benefits and Advantages, and ſuch as keep up the vital Heat and Vigour of the State, purging it from all malignant and corrupted Humours. In theſe are repos'd a vaſt and mighty Truſt; and being plac'd in ſuch exalted Stations, they never want Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of doing of much Good or much Injury. But conſidering the innumerable Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Humane Paſſions and Inclinations, they often meet with great Temptations to miſlead them: And tho the Greatneſs of their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and the Plentifulneſs of their Revenues, may well be ſuppos'd to ſet them above all <hi>common</hi> Attacks, yet it muſt be their Vertues alone that can ſecure them againſt ſuch as are <hi>Extraor dinary.</hi> Therefore the good King <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat,</hi> when he ſet Judges over the Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> gave this moſt remarkable Charge to them; <hi>Take heed what you do; for ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the Judgment. Wherefore now, let the Fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed and do it: for there is no Iniquity with the Lord our God, nor Reſpect of Perſons, nor taking of Gifts,</hi> 2 Chron. c. 19. v. 6, 7. There cannot be a greater Motive and ſtronger Argument than the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135143:8"/> Words of theſe two Verſes: And were I to enter upon them, and inſiſt upon all their Particulars, I ſhou'd ſeem to deviate too much from my firſt Subject and Deſign, which was to ſay ſomething of the Cares and Duties not only of Judges, but likewiſe of all ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Perſons who depend upon them, and are concern'd in this preſent Publick Occaſion.</p>
            <p>And here I might not improperly inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe great Conveniencies and mighty Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which the Nation receives from theſe publick Meetings and Adminiſtrations of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and what Good the Judges and their Miniſters are capable of doing. And more eſpecially I might inſiſt upon thoſe ſeveral Acts of Injuſtice which are <hi>ſometimes</hi> done by Judges themſelves, but <hi>more frequently</hi> by Lawyers and Officers of the Court. <hi>Theſe</hi> do moſt properly belong to my preſent Subject and Occaſion: But to ſearch and to dive into all theſe Particulars, as it is a Task exceeding tedious, and almoſt endleſs, ſo it is likewiſe an Office very ungrateful to ſome, and will be thought unmannerly by others. However, I crave leave to ſay ſomething concerning two Particulars, both of which are exceeding Grievances; yet they are by many vindicated,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135143:8"/> and look'd upon as Matters not in themſelves unjuſt. They are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Delaying and deferring of Juſtice when it is really due: And,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Knowingly to undertake and manage an unjuſt Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt Particular belongs principally to the Judges, and the ſecond to the Lawyers and Officers; and the One is frequently the Cauſe of the Other.</p>
            <p>1. Delaying and deferring of Juſtice when it is really due. This, with Submiſſion, I take to be a notorious Piece of Injuſtice. For, whenſoever it is in the <hi>Power</hi> of the Judge and the Court to do a Man Juſtice that ſues for his real Rights, and they wilfully defer and delay it, it is undoubtedly unjuſt, and <hi>an Abomination to the Lord.</hi> The detaining and keeping a Perſon from his Right, is a manifeſt Injury to him, and ſometimes occaſions the Loſs of it at laſt; but very often it makes it ſo inconvenient and burdenſom to him, that it wou'd have been as well, or perhaps better for him to have loſt it at firſt. Whether this growing Miſchief has aroſe from the Number and Variety of our Laws and Caſes, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Liberty of our State and Conſtitution, the Methods and Practices of the Courts of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135143:9"/> or from the unreaſonable Compliance of the Judges themſelves, or from all theſe together, I ſhall not pretend to determine. For my own Part, I ſhall only take the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to ſay, That the Tediouſneſs of many of our Law-Suits, and the frequent Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of obtaining Juſtice, are become a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den almoſt inſupportable to this Nation; and a Burden from which many barbarous, and I may add, inſlav'd Nations are in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure free. Theſe <hi>Regular Proceedings</hi> are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the honourable Badges and Tokens of our Liberties; but as they are often ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd, they are grown ſo heavy and grievous to us, that Fetters and Chains are almoſt as eligible.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, that theſe are Miſchiefs and Misfortunes that do chiefly attend the moſt civiliz'd and polite, as well as the moſt free and eaſie Governments. For in the Beginning and Infancy of Kingdoms and Common-Wealths, the Laws are generally few and ſtrict, the Suits eaſie and ſoon determin'd, ſo that Juſtice is continually done without any Trouble or Burden. Then <hi>Juſtice</hi> is a Lady free and generous, modeſt, yet eaſie of Acceſs, and ready to aſſiſt all that ſue to Her. But when Dominions and Policy, Laws and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135143:9"/> Arts and Sciences, and Riches and Vices encreaſe, then <hi>Juſtice</hi> is diſguis'd, and attended with ſuch numerous Trains, and muſt be waited upon with ſuch Variety of Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and pretended Regularities, that but few can be able to approach her Preſence. The Poor cannot purchaſe their Way through her Attendants, but muſt be ſatisfied without her Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Now it is generally acknowledg'd, That nothing ſo much enervates the Strength of a State, and relaxes the Sinews of a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as ſlow and dilatory Proceedings in Matters of Juſtice. They fill the Body Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick with ill and unwholeſom Humours for want of Exerciſe and Evacuation, and do in a great meaſure make the Blood and Spirits to ſtagnate. They make Way for all Kinds of Corruptions, and all Kinds of vile Practices; and have been the Cauſe of the Decay and Mortality of the greateſt Empires and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealths in the World.</p>
            <p>The Danger of theſe was ſoon diſcover'd by the great Emperor <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> who when he came to reform and revive a corrupted and ſinking Empire, he found it abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to regulate the Tediouſneſs of Law Suits, and to retrench the innumerable Proceſſes and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135143:10"/> Appeals in the Courts of Judicature; without which the State it ſelf muſt have ſuffer'd. His Example was happily follow'd by his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Son <hi>Titus,</hi> and alſo by the renowned <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan,</hi> who beſides theſe Regulations, utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminated all the <hi>Delators, Promoters,</hi> and <hi>Pettifoggers</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> and put them to all Kinds of ignominious Puniſhments, as the Peſts of the City, and the Diſturbers of the Publick Peace. The Care and Wiſdom of theſe Princes recover'd the State, and kept it alive for ſome Ages longer than cou'd have reaſonably been expected. To deſcend to a more modern Inſtance, I might mention the preſent <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, which is acknowledg'd by all to be overgrown with ſuch notorious Corruptions and Briberies, and to abound with ſuch Flaws in Policy, as are ſufficient to ſink that or any other State: Yet we are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by the moſt skilful Politicians, That this Empire is kept up by almoſt one Thing alone; which is, The extraordinary quick Diſpatch in all Matters of Juſtice. This does in a great meaſure ſet all Things right, and makes Amends for all the other Errors and falſe Steps in the Government.</p>
            <p>I do not pretend to propoſe any of theſe Examples for our own Imitation, but only
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135143:10"/> mention them to ſhow the fatal Miſchiefs of dilatory Proceedings in Juſtice, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of the contrary Practices. And for that I might produce great Numbers of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; but I am ſatisfied that I need not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal either to Hiſtory or Example, to prove ſo manifeſt a Truth. It is ſufficient for me to ſhow, That theſe are real Acts of Injuſtice, and are never to be allow'd when it is in the <hi>Power</hi> of Judges and Magiſtrates to prevent them. And I may add, That tho' Judges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways act by a limited Power, which the Laws themſelves do ſometimes ſtreighten to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient Degree; yet ſtill they have a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Relieving, if not Remedying theſe Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs in moſt Caſes. I hope I reflect upon none here preſent, when I ſay, It is a Shame to good Men, and a Wonder to wiſe Men, That ſuch frivolous Pleas, and ſuch ridiculous Niceties ſhou'd be <hi>urg'd</hi> and <hi>allow'd</hi> in Courts of Judicature, as we often find; and all this to ward off a preſent Blow, and to hinder a Man as much as poſſible of his real Rights and Eſtate. This may truly be call'd <hi>a falſe Balance</hi> and an <hi>Abomination:</hi> For this is doing a Perſon an Injury, and then ſhowing him Law for it; which is abuſing him beſides, and likewiſe ſcandalizing and profaning our Laws,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135143:11"/> which were never made to do or countenance any Piece of Injuſtice. Now one great Cauſe of theſe tedious and unreaſonable Proceſſes in Law, is,</p>
            <p>2. The Other Particular which I propos'd to treat of: Which is, Knowingly to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take and manage an unjuſt Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Now this is a Matter that does not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belong to Judges of Courts, as to <hi>Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>Advocates;</hi> and it is ſo frequently pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd in all Courts, that by many it is not only thought to be no Sin, but a Thing very convenient and neceſſary. But I am ſatisfied that nothing is more eaſily prov'd than the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and Sinfulneſs of ſuch Practices. For he who knowingly promotes and willingly joins with a Perſon in an unjuſt Cauſe, is no leſs guilty than the Perſon himſelf, and very often more; for the Client is not ſo proper a Judge of the Juſtneſs of a Cauſe as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor is. How often does a juſt Cauſe and a juſt Man ſuffer by theſe Means? When a Pleader ſhall employ the utmoſt of his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, Wit, and Learning, to promote a manifeſt Piece of Injuſtice, and to ruin ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man's juſt Rights? A Thing which, God knows, has too frequently ſucceeded in this Nation. This is the more dangerous and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135143:11"/> fatal, becauſe Quirks and Artifices are never wanting to diſguiſe the Juſtice of the Matter, and to gild over the Blackneſs of the Crime, which are ſometimes ſubtle enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the greateſt Lawyers and Judges them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But it is commonly alledg'd and objected in the Caſe, That <hi>Pleaders</hi> and <hi>Advocates</hi> need not concern themſelves with the Juſtice of a Cauſe; but it is their ſole Employment to aſſiſt their Clients, and do them what Service they can: So that if the Cauſe be bad, it is their Client's Fault, and not theirs, who only act according as their Buſineſs and Profeſſions lead them.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to which Objection, I muſt take leave to aſſert, That no Mans lawful Buſineſs and Employment can neceſſarily lead him to commit an unjuſt Action: And to ſay, He is oblig'd to it by his Profeſſion, is a notorious Reflexion upon his Profeſſion; which is to ſuppoſe that his Profeſſion obliges him to do that which God himſelf has always prohibited. But to put this Matter beyond all Diſpute, I wou'd demand of Him who knowingly pleads and promotes an unjuſt Cauſe, Whether he enters upon it with an Expectation of carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, or not? If he expects and endeavours
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135143:12"/> to carry the Cauſe, he then does Injuſtice to the contrary Party whom he oppoſes, by hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering or endeavouring to hinder him of his real Right: If he does not expect to carry it, he betrays and injures his own Client, which is no leſs unjuſt than the other. So that take it either Way, tho' it may ſometimes be pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liated and extenuated, it can never be vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated. And it is a Surpriſe to good Men ſometimes to ſee Perſons of no common Parts and Learning ſtanding up openly and before the World, to ſmooth over an odious Cauſe, and vindicate an Action in its ſelf manifeſtly unjuſt. This indeed is ſinning with Security, and without Shame; and acting wickedly without either Fear or Remorſe. Certainly ſuch Pleadings muſt prove mightily to their Diſreputation, and be a great Hinderance to their Buſineſs and Profeſſions. But I hope, and am fully perſwaded, that this Audience is free from ſuch Perſons as I am condemning; therefore I wou'd not be thought to reflect upon any here preſent.</p>
            <p>Having briefly gone through theſe two Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars I propos'd, I ſhall omit many other unjuſt Practices that are too frequent in Courts of Judicature, and ſhall only obſerve in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, That all ſuch Acts of Injuſtice as are done
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135143:12"/> in publick Courts, and by publick Perſons, are of the blackeſt Dye, and the moſt odious before God; being always of a higher Concern, and of a more pernicious Conſequence than the unjuſt Actions of private Men. Judges and Magiſtrates have the Stamp of Heaven upon them, and in their Diſtributions of Juſtice do in ſome meaſure repreſent the great Judge of all the Earth. Now if <hi>They,</hi> who are ſet up purpoſely to do Juſtice to others, ſhall commit any Errors, and make any falſe Steps, as they are moſt injurious to the Publick, ſo they are moſt dangerous and fatal to themſelves; and the greater and more exalted the Perſons are, the more hainous are their Crimes.</p>
            <p>Tho the Actions of Judges and Magiſtrates are ſeldom publickly cenſur'd, and more rarely puniſh'd in this World, yet the Supreme Judge of all Men will remember them, and do them Juſtice too, by making them eternal Examples of his Wrath and Vengeance. When that terrible Judge ſhall at the laſt great Day do Juſtice to all Mankind; when all the Myſteries of Iniquity ſhall be unfolded, and all Mens ſecret Thoughts and monſtrous Imaginations be expos'd in their native Deformity to the World; then ſhall the Actions of all unjuſt Judges, Magiſtrates, and Officers be laid open in the moſt publick and exemplary Manner, and be puniſh'd, not as the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135143:13"/> Actions of Single Men, but as the Crimes of whole Societies. To whom much is given, much will be requir'd; and a Man had a thouſand times better be an Ideot, a Natural, and the moſt vile and deſpicable of all Humane Kind, than by his great Parts and Learning to raiſe himſelf to the higheſt Stations, and act contrary to his Truſt. Parts and Learning are moſt dangerous Engines when miſapply'd; and a Man had far better be without them, than to abuſe them. To ſpeak in the plaineſt Terms, A Man had much better be a Fool than a Knave; tho' the former is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally more deſpicable in the Eye of the World. For Folly is only a Misfortune, and the unhappy Effects of meer Nature; but Knavery is a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter begotten by the Devil, which will certainly carry a Man to the black Place where it had its Birth.</p>
            <p>To conclude all, The Matters that I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on are of the higheſt Importance, both to the Honour of God, and to the publick Peace of the Nation; and as I have taken the Freedom to ſpeak ſome Truths without Fear or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance, ſo I hope I have ſpoken them without either Rudeneſs or Indecency.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to God the Father, to God the Son, and to God the Holy-Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory, now and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
